<sect1 id='idtone'>
<title>Identify tone</title>
<informalfigure id="idtone-screen1">
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="figures/idtone.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>Screenshot of the program.</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
</informalfigure>

<para>
This is a combined tone memory and interval exercise. Some people believe this
kind of exercise can give you perfect pitch (absolute pitch), but I don't
believe so.
</para>

<para>The basics are: the program play a tone and you must identify it by
comparing it with the last tone played for you.
</para>

<para>To get you started the program will play one tone and display its name on
the status bar. You identify the tones by clicking on the piano keyboard or
using the keyboard shortcuts that are the letters written on each key.
</para>

<para>Right click on the piano keyboard to hear a note without actually
guessing it. (Some will call that cheating....)</para>

<para>Solfege have a set of exercises that you can find by clicking
“Identify tone” on the front page. You should start with the first
exercise, and move to the next each time you can practise from some
minutes and still have quite a good score, for example 96% correct.</para>

<sect2 id='idtone-manual-conf'>
<title>Manual configuration</title>

<para>You can configure this exercise as you like if you select select
“Configure yourself” front the default front page.</para>

<para>There are several ways you can use this exercise. Personally, I have not used this exercise very much, and the sections below are only suggestions. 
</para>

<sect3 id='idtone-note-by-note'>
<title>Note by note</title>
<para>
Start with only the notes c-d-e at weight 1. When your score is at least 96%
correct, you add the tone f and continue. Add one new tone until you practise
with all 12 tones. Doing this is the same as using the predefined exercises and
following the instructions in the start of this chapter.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id='idtone-heavy-a'>
<title>Heavy A</title>

<para>Configure with the tone a at weight 11 (or higher) and the rest of the tones at weight 1. This way the program will play the tone a very often, so you will remember the tone, and then you use a as a reference tone to identify the other tones. When you have practised a while, you can reduce the weight of a to make the exercise harder.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id='idtone-config'>
<title>Config</title>

<para>If run from “Configure yourself”, on the top of the config page you tell
the program how important the different tones are. If you for example give the
tone a 11 points and the rest 1 point each, then (11+11*1)/11*100 = 50% of the
random tones will be an a.</para>

<para>Below that you select what octaves the random tones can be from.</para>

<para>Then you can select if Solfege should give you a new question
automatically when you have solved the old.</para>

<para>In the frame below you can set some pretty self explaining options about
what happens if you answer wrong.</para>

<para>The keyboard shortcuts can be configured from the 
<link linkend='preferences-window'>preferences window</link>.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
