<sect1 id='preferences-window'>
<title>Preferences window</title>
<sect2 id='pw-midi-stuff'>
<title>Instruments</title>
<informalfigure id="preferences-midi">
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="figures/preferences-midi.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>Screenshot of the 'Midi' page of the preferences window.</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
</informalfigure>
<sect3 id='pw-tempo'>
<title>Tempo</title>
<!-- translators: don't translate the module names in this paragraph. -->
<para>Set the tempo (beats per minute) for music and arpeggios. These values
are used by exercises written with these exercise modules:
<literal>compareintervals</literal>,
<literal>harmonicintervals</literal>,
<literal>idtone</literal>,
<literal>melodicinterval</literal>,
<literal>singchord</literal>,
<literal>singinterval</literal>,
<literal>twelvetone</literal>,
<literal>rhythm</literal>,
<literal>identifybpm</literal>,
<literal>nameinterval</literal>.
Other exercises will either have the tempo set in the lesson file or
on the config page of the exercise.
</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id='pw-preferred-instr'>
<title>Preferred instrument</title>
<para>Set the midi instrument and volume used for most exercises.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id='pw-chord-instr'>
<title>Chord instruments</title>
<para>Solfege can use three different instruments when playing chords. One for
the highest tone, one for the tones in the middle and one for the bass tone.
This can be helpful if you find it difficult to hear individual tones in
chords.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3 id='pw-perc-instr'>
<title>Preferred percussion instruments</title>
<para>
Set the percussion instrument used for count-in before rhythm questions, and
the instrument used to play the question.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id='pw-user'>
<title>User</title>
<informalfigure id="preferences-user">
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="figures/preferences-user.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>Screenshot of the 'User' page of the preferences window.</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
</informalfigure>

<para>Solfege uses this info in some exercises where the user is supposed to sing.</para>
<sect3 id='pw-low-high'>
<title>Lowest/highest tone the user can sing</title>
<para>These spin buttons tell Solfege the highest and lowest tone the user can
sing. These values are only considered advisory by the program.  If for example
the values are set to <literal>c</literal> to <literal>c'</literal> and you
have configured the program to ask you to sing minor and major tenths, you will
have to sing tones outside this range.</para> </sect3>

<sect3 id='pw-sex'>
<title>Sex</title>
<para>Solfege need to know if the user is male or female when creating
some of the questions where the user will sing the answer. This because
the male voice sound one octave lower than the female voice.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2 id='pw-external-programs'>
<title>External programs</title>
<informalfigure id="preferences-external-programs-screenshot">
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="figures/preferences-external-programs.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>Screenshot of the 'External programs' page of the preferences window.</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
</informalfigure>

<para>Solfege will search the PATH for the programs you enter on this page.
So you only have to enter the full path if the programs are installed
outside the PATH. A warning sign after the entry where you enter the file
name mean that the program is not found.</para>

<para>Please check the download page on <ulink
url="http://www.solfege.org">www.solfege.org</ulink> for up-to-date tips
and download links if you run MS Windows and have to download and install
the programs yourself.
</para>

<sect3 id='pw-convertors'>
<title>Converters</title>
<para>Give command lines that can convert between different audio formats.
<literal>%(in)s</literal> will be replaced with the name of the file we convert
from, and <literal>%(out)s</literal> with the name we convert to.
It is not necessary to enter <literal>%(out)s</literal> if the program
automatically saved to a new file with the correct file extension.</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id='pw-audio-players'>
<title>Audio players</title>
<para>Command lines that can play different audio formats.
<literal>%s</literal> will be replaced with the name of the file to be played.
The file name will be appended to the end of the string if you do not include a
<literal>%s</literal>.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3 id='pw-misc'>
<title>Miscellaneous</title>
<para>A few exercises make use of the programs CSound and MMA.
Lilypond-book is required to make ear training test printouts,
and latex is required if the printout should be created in dvi format.
Without latex, you can still create html output.
</para>

<para>If the file entered is a file ending with <literal>.py</literal>,
        then the script will be run by the same python interpreter as
        Solfege itself.</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>
<sect2 id="preferences-gui">
<title>Interface</title>
<informalfigure id="preferences-gui-screenshot">
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="figures/preferences-gui.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>Screenshot of the 'Interface' page of the preferences window.</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
</informalfigure>

<para>Resizeable main window: Allow the user to resize the main
solfege window.</para>
<para>Select language: You can manually select the language you want if
Solfege does not detect this correctly, or if you want to run Solfege
with a different language that your operating system.</para>

<sect3>
<title>Identify tone keyboard accelerators</title>
<informalfigure id="preferences-gui-idtone-accels">
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="figures/preferences-gui-idtone.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>Screenshot of the 'Interface' page of the preferences window.</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
</informalfigure>
<para>
Here you can change the keyboard accelerators for the «Identify tone» exercise.
Click on a row to select the tone you want to change the accelerator for,
then click again on the second column of the row. Finally you can press
the key you want to set as the accel for the tone.
</para>
<para>
The «Dvorak» and «ASCII» buttons will set the accelerators to the
default values for Dvorak and ASCII keyboards.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Interval keyboard accelerators</title>
<informalfigure id="preferences-gui-interval-accels">
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="figures/preferences-gui-interval.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>Screenshot of the 'Interface' page of the preferences window.</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
</informalfigure>
<para>
Here you can change the keyboard accelerators for the interval exercises,
like the «Harmonic interval» and «Melodic interval» exercises.
Click on a row to select the tone you want to change the accelerator for,
then click again on the second column of the row. Finally you can press
the key you want to set as the accel for the tone.
</para>
<para>
The «Dvorak» and «ASCII» buttons will set the accelerators to the
default values for Dvorak and ASCII keyboards.
</para>
</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2 id='pw-practise'>
<title>Practise</title>
<informalfigure id="preferences-practise">
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="figures/preferences-practise.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>Screenshot of the 'Practise' page of the preferences window.</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
</informalfigure>
<para>Not allow new question before the old is solved: Disable the 'new' button until the question is answered correctly or the user clicks "give up".</para>
<para>Repeat question if the answer was wrong: Play the sound again when the user gives an incorrect answer.</para>
<para>Expert mode: Enabling this option in exercises using the
 <link linkend='idbyname-module'>idbyname</link> and
 <link linkend='idproperty-module'>idproperty</link> modules
 will let you select to practise only a subset of the questions
 in the lesson file. Practising with expert mode enabled will not save
 any statistics.</para>
</sect2>

<sect2 id='pw-sound-setup'>
<title>Sound setup</title>
<informalfigure id="preferences-sound-setup">
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="figures/preferences-sound-setup.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>Screenshot of the 'Sound setup' page of the preferences window.</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
</informalfigure>
<informalfigure id="preferences-sound-setup-wib32">
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="figures/preferences-sound-setup-win32.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>Screenshot of the 'Sound setup' page of the preferences window, running on MS Windows XP.</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
</informalfigure>
<sect3 id='pw-midi-setup'>
<title>Midi setup</title>
<variablelist>
<title>The exercises that generate sound have several ways to play sound:</title>
<varlistentry>
<term>No sound:</term>
<listitem>
<para>Use this for debugging or when you are porting Solfege. No sounds are played, the midi events are printed to stdout.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>Use ALSA device</term>
<listitem>
<para>If you have the Python modules for ALSA installed, you can use the
ALSA sequencer. If your operating system is GNU/Linux, you have a menu item on
the Help menu that can download and compile the modules for you.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>Use device:</term>
<listitem>
<para>The best choice here is usually <filename>/dev/music</filename>
because it has the best support for percussion instruments.
<filename>/dev/sequencer2</filename> is usually a symbolic link to
<filename>/dev/music</filename>. If your system don't have
<filename>/dev/music</filename>, you can create it with this command as root (if you run the linux kernel version 2.2 or later):</para>
<para>cd /dev mknod music u 14 8</para>
<para>On MS Windows this choice is labeled <literal>Windows multimedia output</literal>.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>Use external midiplayer:</term>
<listitem>
<para>This can be useful when porting to systems that don't use OSS, or if you have a bad midi synth on your soundcard and want to use timidity.</para>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</sect3>
</sect2>
<sect2 id="pw-statistics">
<title>Statistics</title>
<informalfigure id="preferences-statistics">
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="figures/preferences-statistics.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>Screenshot of the 'Sound setup' page of the preferences window.</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
</informalfigure>
<sect3>
<title>Statistics from 3.15 and older</title>
<para>Versions of Solfege before 3.16.0 saved statistics in many small
files. Solfege 3.16.0 and newer will import these files into the new database
file the first time the program is run, but it will leave the old files on
your computer. It is safe to delete these files after you have run solfege
3.16.0 or newer once. The files are stored in the <literal>statistics</literal>
directory of the <emphasis>application data</emphasis> directory.</para>
</sect3>
<sect3>
  <title>Statistics</title>
  <para>Statistics are now saved in a file <literal>statistics.sqlite</literal>
  in the <emphasis>application data</emphasis> directory. The exact
  location of the directory can be found by selecting
  <guimenuitem>File Locations</guimenuitem> on the <guimenu>Help</guimenu>
  menu. Click <guibutton>Delete</guibutton> to reset you statistics and
  start with an empty <literal>statistics.sqlite</literal> file.</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>
</sect1>
