<sect1 id='trainingset-editor'>
<title>Training set editor</title>
<informalfigure>
  <screenshot>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="figures/trainingset-editor.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject>
        <phrase>Screenshot of the trainingset-editor window.</phrase>
      </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </screenshot>
</informalfigure>
<para>The training set editor lets you create MIDI/WAV/MP3/OGG files of questions
so that you can upload them to your pda, cell phone or MP3 player. A solution
sheet will be generated for you to print out. Then you can let the MP3 player
play the tracks in random order, and you can use the solution sheet to check
if you recognized the music correctly.</para>

<para>You use the training set editor to define which exercises to generate.
You can save your definition in a file for later use. Each time you click
<guibutton>Export</guibutton> a new set of files are generated
in a directory of your choice. You have to manually upload the generated
sound files to you mobile device.</para>

<para>The program let you generate questions from as many lesson files
as you like, but the most typical usage would be to generate lots of questions
from just a single, or just a few files.</para>

<para>The programs used to convert between the different file formats
are defined in Gui page of the
<link linkend='preferences-gui'>preferences window</link>.
Please check the definitions there if you have problems converting the
MIDI files to WAV, MP3 or OGG format.</para>

<variablelist>
<title>Table headings explained</title>
<varlistentry>
 <term>Count</term>
 <listitem><para>The number of questions to generate from the lesson file.
 </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
 <term>Repeat</term>
 <listitem><para>The number of times to repeat each question.
 </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
 <term>Delay</term> <listitem><para>
   How long delay it will be between the questions. Measured in
   the length of quarter-notes.
 </para></listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>

</sect1>
